[
    {
        "question": "Approximately how many years did the Little Ice Age last?",
        "a": "1,000",
        "b": "750",
        "c": "550",
        "d": "220",
        "e": "130",
        "correct_answer": "c"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following events occurred FIRST?",
        "a": "the Counter-Reformation",
        "b": "the end of the Little Ice Age",
        "c": "Christopher Columbus’ expedition to America",
        "d": "the Dutch Empire finds a maritime route to China",
        "e": "the Black Death outbreak",
        "correct_answer": "e"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following events was a leading cause of the Little Ice Age?",
        "a": "anthropogenic effects",
        "b": "large-scale storms",
        "c": "carbon sequestration",
        "d": "tectonic drift",
        "e": "solar minima",
        "correct_answer": "e"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where were glacial advances MOST prevalent during the Little Ice Age?",
        "a": "the Sahara",
        "b": "the Black Sea",
        "c": "the Andes",
        "d": "the Alps",
        "e": "the Gobi Desert",
        "correct_answer": "d"
    },
    {
        "question": "How many major cooling periods did the Little Ice Age contain?",
        "a": "five",
        "b": "one",
        "c": "three",
        "d": "six",
        "e": "two",
        "correct_answer": "c"
    },
    {
        "question": "The classical interpretation of the world’s climate used by early European explorers held that world conditions were all similar to",
        "a": "Scandinavia",
        "b": "Mesopotamia",
        "c": "the Alps",
        "d": "the British Isles",
        "e": "the Mediterranean",
        "correct_answer": "e"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following European nations did NOT form a major empire in the sixteenth century?",
        "a": "Germany",
        "b": "Great Britain",
        "c": "France",
        "d": "Spain",
        "e": "Portugal",
        "correct_answer": "a"
    },
    {
        "question": "How did the cold spell of the 1590s affect British colonialism?",
        "a": "Settlers cooperated with Native Americans more during hard times.",
        "b": "Famine caused many British colonies to fail.",
        "c": "Increased rainfall caused colonial crops to flourish and expanded trade.",
        "d": "Cold waters changed oceans currents and disrupted colonial trade routes.",
        "e": "Lack of resources at home encouraged the British poor to immigrate.",
        "correct_answer": "e"
    },
    {
        "question": "What complication hindered development of a Dutch trade route to China?",
        "a": "severe storms",
        "b": "naval resistance",
        "c": "piracy",
        "d": "poor navigation",
        "e": "frozen seas",
        "correct_answer": "e"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following effects of the Little Ice Age was the MOST prominent in Africa?",
        "a": "tornadoes",
        "b": "ground frost",
        "c": "tropical storms",
        "d": "droughts",
        "e": "flooding",
        "correct_answer": "d"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the Little Ice Age, monsoons were a persistent threat in",
        "a": "Oceania",
        "b": "the Middle East",
        "c": "the Amazon Rainforest",
        "d": "East Asia",
        "e": "the Caribbean",
        "correct_answer": "d"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following locations was the site of colonial conflict between the French, British, and Spanish?",
        "a": "British Columbia",
        "b": "Haiti",
        "c": "New York",
        "d": "Florida",
        "e": "Nova Scotia",
        "correct_answer": "d"
    },
    {
        "question": "Why did climate conditions worsen European relations with Native Americans?",
        "a": "Mist, storms, and snow provided cover that enabled attacks.",
        "b": "Conditions made travel from Europe easier.",
        "c": "Ships sunk by storms were attributed to Native American attacks.",
        "d": "Europeans blamed bad weather on Native American paganism.",
        "e": "The groups competed for limited food.",
        "correct_answer": "e"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following intellectual ages occurred MOST recently?",
        "a": "the Enlightenment",
        "b": "the Scientific Revolution",
        "c": "the Renaissance",
        "d": "the Reformation",
        "e": "the Classical Era",
        "correct_answer": "a"
    },
    {
        "question": "How did the weather patterns of the late Holocene affect the development of European society?",
        "a": "They made people more superstitious.",
        "b": "They caused people to turn to science rather than religion.",
        "c": "They dramatically diminished the population.",
        "d": "They encouraged empires to develop centralized organizations.",
        "e": "They strengthened the centralization of the Catholic Church.",
        "correct_answer": "d"
    }
]
